Register to the Winifred Armstrong papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Winifred Armstrong papers
1920-1995
2012C52
Hoover Institution Archives
57 manuscript boxes, 1 sound recording reel (23.8 linear feet)
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, studies, bulletins, and printed matter, relating to political, social and economic conditions in Africa; mining and mineral resources in Africa; American and international business investment in Africa; American foreign policy and developmental assistance in Africa; and environmental issues in Africa.
Armstrong, Winifred.
Access
The collection is open for research. The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2012.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Winifred Armstrong, an American economist, had a longstanding interest in Africa. She was a staff member on the United States Foreign Relations Committee's Subcommittee on Africa, chaired by Senator John F. Kennedy, from 1959 to 1960. Subsequently she was employed from 1966 to 1975 as international economist by AMAX, Inc., an international mining corporation with headquarters in New York. There her work focused on AMAX operations in Africa. She is co-author with Theodore Geiger of The Development of African Private Enterprise (New York: National Planning Association, 1964).
Scope and Content of Collection
The Winifred Armstrong Papers in the Hoover Institution Archives are drawn from her work as international economist for AMAX from 1966 to 1975. AMAX (formerly American Metal Climax Corporation) carried out copper mining operations in Botswana, Namibia, South Africa and Zambia. Several other corporations were linked with AMAX as associates or subsidiaries. These included the Roan Selection Trust (of which AMAX was part owner, and which operated in Zambia), Botswana RST (its subsidiary in Botswana), the Newmont Mining Corporation and its subsidiaries, the Tsumeb Corporation (in Namibia) and the O'okiep Copper Company (in Namibia and South Africa). The Anglo American Corporation of South Africa partnered with AMAX in ownership of the Roan Selection Trust. In 1969 the Zambian government initiated nationalization of its mineral resources, taking over a 51% interest in the Roan Selection Trust, with AMAX remaining as a minority shareholder. Copper mining operations in Zambia were carried out by the government-controlled Roan Consolidated Mines, Mindeco, and Nchanga Consolidated Mines from 1970 on.
The 1966-1975 period of Winifred Armstrong's employment with AMAX coincided with the early years of independence of Zambia and Botswana, achieved in 1964 and 1966 respectively. The status of Namibia (then South West Africa) was in dispute throughout this period, with efforts in the United Nations to revoke the governance mandate granted to South Africa in the aftermath of World War I. South Africa itself was under increasing international pressure due to its apartheid policies, as was Rhodesia (now Zimbabwe).
The Winifred Armstrong Papers document not only mining industry activities within Botswana, Namibia, South Africa and Zambia, but also the larger diplomatic, political, economic, and social contexts within which they took place, including issues of foreign investment in newly independent countries, their development strategies, and advocacy of divestment from apartheid regimes. They include numerous bulletins and memoranda written by Winifred Armstrong to keep AMAX officers abreast of changing situations, and notes and memoranda on corporate decisions and deliberations. There is also a large quantity of collected reports, studies and statistics, published and unpublished, from governmental and nongovernmental sources, on political, social and economic conditions in these four countries and also in other countries of Africa during the late colonial and early national periods. A small number of items date after 1975.
A smaller but significant portion of the collection deals with the AMAX response to growing concerns in the late 1960s and early 1970s regarding the environmental impact of mining operations. It includes documentation of the work of AMAX's Environmental Planning and Protection Committee and its interactions with governmental environmental agencies and nongovernmental environmental advocacy groups.
The papers of Winifred Armstrong are dispersed. She donated her AMAX papers to the Hoover Institution Archives in 2012. Her papers regarding her work with John F. Kennedy on the Senate Foreign Relations Committee are in the John F. Kennedy Presidential Library. Other papers on Africa are in the Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture at the New York Public Library. Other papers on environmental issues are at the Pace University School of Law. Other papers on economic issues are at the Special Collections Research Center of Temple University. Still other smaller files on these and New York City neighborhood issues are located elsewhere.
Arrangement
The collection has been arranged in three series: AMAX Office File, 1961-1975, Subject File, 1920-1995, and Audiovisual File, 1969-1973.
Related Collection(s)
Winifred Armstrong Personal Papers, John F. Kennedy Presidential Library and Museum
Armstrong, Winifred/South Africa, Schomburg Center for Research in Black Culture, The New York Public Library
AMAX, Inc.; Africa--Economic conditions.; Africa--Foreign relations--United States.; Africa--Politics and government.; Africa--Social conditions.; Business enterprises--Africa.; Economic assistance--Africa.; Environmental protection--Africa.; Mines and mineral resources--Africa.; United States--Foreign relations--Africa.
- AMAX Office File, 1961-1975. (Box 1-9)
  Scope and Contents note
  - General. Brochures, press releases, memoranda, speeches by AMAX officers, and miscellaneous informational material about AMAX, 1961-1973 (Folder 1: 1-2)
  - AMAX Foundation. Correspondence, memoranda and reports re AMAX Foundation grants for charitable purposes, 1970-1975 (Folder 1: 3)
  - article reprints, 1970-1972 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Annual meetings. Annual meeting reports and preparatory materials for annual meetings, 1972-1974 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Chronological file. Carbon copies of letters and memoranda by Winifred Armstrong, arranged chronologically
    - 1965 (Folder 2: 1)
    - 1966 (Folder 2: 2)
    - 1967 (Folder 3: 1)
    - 1968 (Folder 3: 2)
    - 1969 (Folder 4: 1)
    - 1970 (Folder 4: 2)
    - 1971 (Folder 4: 3)
    - 1972 (Folder 5: 1)
    - 1973 (Folder 5: 2)
    - 1974 (Folder 6: 1)
  - Correspondence. Other correspondence is filed in the Subject File
    - General, 1965-1972 (Folder 6: 2)
    - Hochschild, Harold K. (AMAX director; African American Institute chair), 1962-1974. (Folder 6: 3)
    - Hochshild, Walter, 1968-1974 (Folder 6: 4)
    - Ingersoll, Jean M., 1972 (Folder 6: 5)
    - Jackson, Barbara Ward, Lady, 1970 (Folder 6: 6)
    - Kennan, George F., 1967-1970 (Folder 6: 7)
    - Mikesell, Raymond F., 1971-1974. (Folder 7: 1)
    - Munger, Edwin S., 1970 (Folder 7: 2)
    - Tore, Rose, 1967-1971 (Folder 7: 3)
  - Environmental Control Conference (1970: Denver). Proceedings of internal AMAX conference (Folder 7: 4)
  - Environmental Handbook, Volume I, 1972 (Folder 7: 5)
  - Environmental Planning and Protection Committee (AMAX internal committee)
    - Internal documents. Minutes, memoranda, studies and reports
      - 1969-1971 (Folder 7: 6)
      - 1972 (Folder 7: 7)
      - 1973 (Folder 8: 1)
    - Public issuances and printed matter re AMAX environmental record
      - 1967-1969 (Folder 8: 2)
      - 1970 (Folder 8: 3)
      - 1971 (Folder 8: 4)
      - 1972 (Folder 8: 5)
      - 1973-1974 (Folder 8: 6)
      - Undated (Folder 8: 7)
    - AMF, Inc. Environmental Report, World Wide Review, 1973 (Folder 8: 8)
  - Kirwin Environmental Study. Reports on environmental impact of mining operations in Kirwin, Wyoming, area, made for AMAX by the Rocky Mountain Center on Environment, 1973 (Folder 9: 1-2)
  - Litigation. Legal briefs, judicial decision and press releases re U.S. Third Circuit Court of Appeals case of Kohn vs. American Metal Climax et al., re amalgamation of Roan Selection Trust into AMAX, 1971-1973 (Folder 9: 3)
  - Student employment. Correspondence, memoranda, reports and printed matter re AMAX student training programs, 1966-1973 (Folder 9: 4)
  - Summary of Weekly News. Correspondence and memoranda re production and distribution of weekly press coverage bulletins by Winifred Armstrong for internal AMAX consumption, 1965-1974. (Folder 9: 5)
- Subject File, 1920-1995. (Box 10-52)
  - Adela Investment Company. Correspondence, memoranda, notes, and reports, 1965-1969 (Folder 10: 1)
  - Africa (general) (Folder 10)
  - Conference papers, 1960-1962 (Folder 10: 2)
  - Printed matter, 1956-1995 (Folder 10: 3)
  - African studies programs. Correspondence, reports, newsletters and lists, 1960-1974 (Folder 10: 4)
  - Agriculture. Reports, press releases, legislative bills and printed articles, 1968-1974. (Folder 10: 5)
  - Algeria. Economic reports, 1970-1973 (Folder 10: 6)
  - Anglo American Corporation of South Africa
    - General. Memoranda, pamphlets and other printed matter, 1956-1967 (Folder 11: 1)
    - issues (published by the Corporation), 1973-1977 (Folder 11: 2)
  - Art and culture. Announcements, reports and press releases, 1961-1974. (Folder 11: 3)
  - Benin (Dahomey). Reports and notes, 1970-1974 (Folder 11: 4)
  - Botswana (Bechuanaland)
    - General. Correspondence, memoranda, bulletins, notes, speeches, reports and printed matter
      - 1965 (Folder 11: 5)
      - 1966 (Folder 11: 6)
      - 1967 (Folder 11: 7)
      - 1968 (Folder 11: 8)
      - 1969 (Folder 12: 1)
      - 1970 (Folder 12: 2)
      - 1971 (Folder 12: 3)
      - 1972 (Folder 12: 4)
      - 1973 (Folder 12: 5)
      - 1974 (Folder 12: 6)
      - Undated (Folder 12: 7)
    - 4-H Club student exchange program. Notes and reports, 1972-1975 (Folder 12: 8)
  - Botswana RST Limited. Memoranda, reports, prospectuses and press releases, 1966-1974. (Folder 13: 1-2)
  - Burkina Faso (Upper Volta). Economic reports, 1969-1970 (Folder 13: 3)
  - Burundi. Correspondence, memoranda, notes and printed matter, 1962-1974 (Folder 13: 4)
  - Cameroon. Letter, press release and printed matter, 1959-1975 (Folder 13: 5)
  - Canada. Memorandum and printed matter, 1970-1974 (Folder 13: 6)
  - Carnegie Corporation. issues, 1962-1974 (Folder 13: 7)
  - Central African Republic. Notes and economic report, 1970-1973 (Folder 13: 8)
  - Chad. Press release and printed matter, 1968-1974 (Folder 13: 9)
  - Chambers of commerce. Correspondence, memoranda and printed matter, re African-American Chamber of Commerce and other African chambers of commerce, 1965-1973 (Folder 13: 10)
  - Chile. Memoranda and printed matter, 1966-1974 (Folder 14: 1)
  - China. Speech and printed matter, mainly re Chinese involvement in Africa, 1963-1972 (Folder 14: 2)
  - Churches. Memoranda, reports and printed matter, mainly re churches in Africa and church involvement in South Africa divestment movements, 1957-1974 (Folder 14: 3)
  - Coal (general). Printed articles, 1974 (Folder 14: 4)
  - Colombia. Printed matter, 1970-1973 (Folder 14: 5)
  - Commission on Critical Choices for Americans. Correspondence, 1974 (Folder 14: 6)
  - Conference Board. Publications re corporate foundations, 1972 (Folder 14: 7)
  - Conference on Opportunities for Trade and Investment in the Developing Countries of Africa (1972: Washington, D.C.). Meeting materials (Folder 14: 8)
  - Conferences (general). Correspondence, meeting materials and printed matter, 1966-1974 (Folder 14: 9)
  - Congo (Brazzaville) (People's Republic of the Congo). Notes and memoranda, 1964-1974 (Folder 14: 10)
  - Congo (Democratic Republic) (Belgian Congo; Zaire). Memoranda, reports, notes, bulletins, studies, press releases and printed matter
    - 1956-1959 (Folder 14: 11)
    - 1960-1969 (Folder 15: 1)
    - 1970-1975 and undated (Folder 15: 2)
  - Containerization. Memoranda, notes and printed matter, 1968 (Folder 15: 3)
  - Copper (general). Memoranda, reports, notes, bulletins, studies and printed matter
    - 1959-1969 (Folder 15: 4)
    - 1970-1974 (Folder 15: 5)
  - Corporate responsibility. Correspondence, memoranda, reports, studies and printed matter, mainly re issues of divestment from South Africa
    - 1966-1969. Includes working materials of Princeton University Ad Hoc Committee on University Investments (Folder 15: 6)
    - 1970-1974 (Folder 16: 1)
  - Cï¿½te d'Ivoire (Ivory Coast)
    - General. Correspondence, notes, memoranda, studies, reports and printed matter, 1960-1974 (Folder 16: 2)
    - Cï¿½te d'Ivoire government publications, including tourist guides, 1965-1972 (Folder 16: 3)
  - Council for International Progress in Management. Memoranda and printed matter, 1967-1968 (Folder 16: 4)
  - Council on Foreign Relations. Correspondence, memoranda, announcements and reports, 1966-1973 (Folder 16: 5)
  - Currencies. Printed articles, 1971 (Folder 17: 1)
  - Data processing. Printed article, 1971 (Folder 17: 2)
  - Depreciation. Printed articles, 1970 (Folder 17: 3)
  - Ditchley Foundation. Report, 1971 (Folder 17: 4)
  - Economy and development. Correspondence, memoranda, bulletins, reports and printed matter. Includes material on the economy and development of Africa
    - 1958-1965 (Folder 17: 5)
    - 1967 (Folder 17: 6)
    - 1970-1974 (Folder 17: 7)
  - Education and training. Correspondence, notes, memoranda, bulletins, reports and printed matter. Includes material on education and training in Africa
    - 1956-1959 (Folder 17: 8)
    - 1960-1968 (Folder 17: 9)
    - 1969 (Folder 18: 1)
    - 1970 (Folder 18: 2)
    - 1971-1974 (Folder 18: 3)
  - Ethiopia. Notes, memoranda, reports and printed matter
    - 1935-1969 (Folder 18: 4)
    - 1970-1974 and undated (Folder 18: 5)
  - European Economic Community. Reports and printed matter re European Economic Community involvement in Africa, 1961-1974 (Folder 19: 1)
  - Famines. Notes, reports and printed matter, 1965-1973. (Folder 19: 2)
  - Ford Foundation. Correspondence, notes, reports and printed matter, mainly re Ford Foundation involvement in Africa, 1957-1974 (Folder 19: 3)
  - Foreign Area Fellowship Program. Memorandum and announcements, 1971-1972 (Folder 19: 4)
  - Foreign private investment. Correspondence, memoranda, studies, reports and printed matter. Includes material on foreign investment in Africa
    - 1963-1970 (Folder 19: 5)
    - 1971-1974 and undated (Folder 19: 6)
  - France and French Africa. Conference papers and printed matter, 1955-1969 (Folder 20: 1)
  - Franklin Book Programs. Correspondence, reports and printed matter, re book publication in developing countries, 1968-1974 (Folder 20: 2)
  - Gabon. Notes and printed matter, 1969-1973 (Folder 20: 3)
  - Gambia. Printed matter, 1962-1967 (Folder 20: 4)
  - Germany. Memoranda and printed matter, 1967-1973. (Folder 20: 5)
  - Ghana. Conference papers, press releases and printed matter, 1958-1968 (Folder 20: 6)
  - Great Britain and British Africa. Correspondence, memoranda and printed matter, 1955-1974 (Folder 20: 7)
  - Guinea. Press release and printed matter, 1963-1971 (Folder 20: 8)
  - Guyana. Printed matter, 1971-1973 (Folder 20: 9)
  - Howard University. Printed data, 1970 (Folder 20: 10)
  - India. Printed matter, 1961-1971 (Folder 20: 11)
  - Indians, American. Correspondence, notes and reports re Economic and Manpower Corporation job training program on the Papago Indian Reservation, Arizona, 1971-1974 (Folder 21: 1)
  - Indonesia. Economic reports and printed matter, 1969-1973 (Folder 21: 2)
  - Industrial Research Institute. Memorandum, 1973 (Folder 21: 3)
  - Innovation Group. Journal re technology, 1970 (Folder 21: 4)
  - Institute for Policy Studies. Memorandum, 1967 (Folder 21: 5)
  - Institute of Current World Affairs. Bulletins re Africa, 1962-1964 (Folder 21: 6)
  - Insurance. Printed article, 1973 (Folder 21: 7)
  - Inter-Governmental Committee of Copper Exporting Countries (CIPEC). Memoranda and printed matter, 1969-1974 (Folder 21: 8)
  - Inter-Governmental Copper Conference (1967: Lusaka). Proceedings (Folder 21: 9)
  - Intermediate Technology Development Group. Correspondence, memoranda and reports, 1965-1970. (Folder 21: 10)
  - International African Institute. Brochures and informational data, 1958 (Folder 21: 11)
  - International Association for the Exchange of Students for Technical Experience. Brochure, undated (Folder 21: 12)
  - International Basic Economy Corporation. Correspondence, memoranda, notes and reports, 1966-1973 (Folder 22: 1)
  - International Executive Service Corps. Printed article, 1970 (Folder 22: 2)
  - International Institute for Environmental Affairs. Brochure, 1972 (Folder 22: 3)
  - International Institute of Differing Civilizations. Informational data, 1967 (Folder 22: 4)
  - International Legal Center. Informational data on projects in Africa, 1967-1968 (Folder 22: 5)
  - International Management and Development Institute. Letter and brochure, 1972 (Folder 22: 6)
  - International Peace Academy. Notes and brochures, 1971-1973 (Folder 22: 7)
  - International statistics. Statistical data, 1972 (Folder 22: 8)
  - International Voluntary Services. Letter and brochure, 1972 (Folder 22: 9)
  - Italy. Printed matter, 1968-1973. (Folder 22: 10)
  - Japan. Printed article re Japanese involvement in Africa, 1970 (Folder 22: 11)
  - Kenya. Correspondence, memoranda, notes, reports, press releases and printed matter
    - 1958-1966 (Folder 22: 12)
    - 1967-1969 (Folder 22: 13)
    - 1970-1972 (Folder 22: 14)
    - 1973-1974 and undated (Folder 23: 1)
  - L. S. B. Leakey Foundation. Correspondence and brochure, 1969 (Folder 23: 2)
  - Labor. Correspondence, reports and printed matter, 1954-1970. (Folder 23: 3)
  - Law. Letter and memorandum re law in Africa, 1974 and undated (Folder 23: 4)
  - Lebanon. Notes, undated (Folder 23: 5)
  - Lesotho (Basutoland). Correspondence, notes, memoranda and printed matter, 1961-1972 (Folder 23: 6)
  - Liberation Committee for Africa. Circulars, ca. 1962 (Folder 23: 7)
  - Liberia
    - General. Memoranda, notes and printed matter, 1953-1974 (Folder 23: 8)
    - Lamco Concession Area School System. Reports, 1973-1974 (Folder 23: 9)
    - Liberian government financial and economic reports, 1973-1974 (Folder 23: 10)
    - Liberian Iron and Steel Corporation concession agreements, 1967-1974 (Folder 24: 1)
  - Lincoln University. International management training program proposal and memoranda, 1967 (Folder 24: 2)
  - Lonrho Limited. Financial data and printed matter re operations in Africa, 1967-1974 (Folder 24: 3)
  - Madagascar (Malagasy Republic). Economic reports, 1966-1973 (Folder 24: 4)
  - Malawi (Nyasaland). Correspondence, notes, memoranda, reports and printed matter, 1962-1973 (Folder 24: 5)
  - Mali. Notes, 1970 (Folder 24: 6)
  - Malta. Printed article, 1970 (Folder 24: 7)
  - Maps of Africa and African countries, 1950-1975 (Folder 24: 8)
  - Mauritania. Notes and printed matter, 1965-1974 (Folder 24: 9)
  - Mauritius. Printed article, 1971 (Folder 24: 10)
  - Mexico. Printed article, 1972 (Folder 24: 11)
  - Mining (general). Speech and printed matter, 1968-1974 (Folder 24: 12)
  - Monetary exchanges. Statistical data, 1971-1973 (Folder 24: 13)
  - Multinational corporations. Notes, memoranda, reports, speeches and printed matter
    - 1967-1972 (Folder 25: 1)
    - 1973 (Folder 25: 2)
    - 1974-1975 and undated (Folder 25: 3)
  - Music, African. Reports and printed matter, 1956-1962 (Folder 25: 4)
  - Namibia (South West Africa)
    - General. Correspondence, memoranda, notes, reports, bulletins, statements, press releases, conference materials, United Nations issuances, International Court of Justice issuances, South African government issuances, South African Institute of Race Relations issuances, South West Africa People's Organization issuances, South West Africa National United Front issuances, and printed matter
      - 1920-1965 (Folder 25: 5)
      - 1966 (Folder 26: 1-2)
      - 1967 (Folder 26: 3)
      - 1968 (Folder 26: 4)
      - 1969 (Folder 26: 5)
      - 1970 (Folder 26: 6)
      - 1971 (Folder 27: 1-2)
      - 1972 (Folder 27: 3-5)
      - 1973 (Folder 28: 1)
      - 1974 (Folder 28: 2)
      - 1975 (Folder 28: 3)
      - 1976 (Folder 28: 4)
      - 1977-1978 (Folder 28: 5)
      - Undated (Folder 28: 6)
    - International Conference on South-West Africa (1966: Oxford University). Letter, list of participants and conference papers (Folder 28: 7)
    - Kuhangua, Jacob (South West Africa People's Organization leader). Correspondence, memoranda and notes, 1966-1968 (Folder 28: 8)
    - Winter, Colin (Bishop of Damaraland). Correspondence, memoranda and writings, 1967-1971 (Folder 29: 1)
  - National Academy of Public Administration. Brochure, 1969 (Folder 29: 2)
  - National Association of Manufacturers. Issuances and printed matter, 1972 (Folder 29: 3)
  - National Council of the Churches of Christ in the U.S.A. Report re involvement in Africa and clipping, 1964-1973 (Folder 29: 4)
  - National Foreign Trade Council. Correspondence, memoranda, notes, speeches, declarations and convention materials. Includes material on Africa
    - 1970-1973 (Folder 29: 5)
    - 1974 (Folder 29: 6)
  - National Planning Association
    - Correspondence, memoranda and notes, 1965-1974 (Folder 29: 7)
    - National Planning Association publications, 1967-1971. (Folder 30: 1)
    - working materials. Reports, conference papers and printed matter collected as research material for National Planning Association booklet by Theodore Geiger and Winifred Armstrong published in 1964
      - 1958-1962 (Folder 30: 2)
      - 1963 (Folder 30: 3)
      - 1964 and undated (Folder 30: 4)
  - Natural resources (general). Notes and printed matter, 1967-1974 (Folder 30: 5)
  - New York. Clippings, 1973-1975 (Folder 30: 6)
  - Newmont Mining Corporation. Correspondence, annual reports and statements re Namibia and South Africa political issues, 1968-1974 (Folder 30: 7)
  - Newspapers of the world. Printed articles, 1965 (Folder 30: 8)
  - Niger. Notes and printed matter, 1969-1970 (Folder 31: 1)
  - Nigeria. Speeches and printed matter, 1960-1974 (Folder 31: 2)
  - Ocean resources. Notes and printed matter, 1969-1974 (Folder 31: 3)
  - Oil. Bulletins and printed matter, 1973-1974 (Folder 31: 4)
  - O'okiep Copper Company. Notes, memoranda, reports and printed matter re mining operations in Namibia and South Africa, 1968-1974 (Folder 31: 5)
  - Opportunities Industrialization Center. Correspondence, 1972 (Folder 31: 6)
  - Organization for Economic Cooperation and Development. Pamphlets, 1973-1974 (Folder 31: 7)
  - Organization of African Unity. Memorandum and pamphlet, 1963-1969 (Folder 31: 8)
  - Overseas Development Council. Bulletins and pamphlets, 1971-1974 (Folder 31: 9)
  - Overseas Private Investment Corporation. Handbook, press release and speech, 1970-1974 (Folder 31: 10)
  - Pan African Business Center. Economic reports and brochures, 1973 (Folder 31: 11)
  - Pan-African Students of America. Memoranda, journal and brochure, 1968 (Folder 31: 12)